Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Impunity and Dictatorship, 1957-2003
  - Jean Dominique assassination, 2000-2004
    - External press and media (1-2 of 21), 2000-2004, bulk 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 132)
      Non-Radio Haiti sources on the assassination of Jean Dominique and the ongoing investigation, from Haiti and abroad. Sources include Le Nouvelliste, Agroculture, Ayiti Fanm, Listín Diario, the Haitian Times, Jounal Bon Nouvèl, Haïti en Marche, La Presse Montréal, Time Magazine, Newsday, Hoy, Haïti Progrès, the New York Times, the New Yorker, Le Matin, l'Union, the Village Voice, Référence, Haiti Press Network, Haïti Observateur, Catholic Worker, and the Washington Post, among others. The Haitian Times includes English translations of Jean Dominique's December 16, 1996 Face à l'Opinion interview with Jean-Bertrand Aristide, and his editorial "Dany Toussaint, prend-il les enfants du bon dieu pour des canards sauvages?"
    - External press and media (3-10 of 21), 2000-2004, bulk 2000-2002; 8 folders (Box 133)
    - External press and media (11-19 of 21), 2000-2004, bulk 2000-2002; 9 folders (Box 134)
    - External press and media (20-21 of 21), 2000-2004, bulk 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 135)
    - Funeral, 2000; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Materials related the funeral for Jean Dominique and Jean-Claude Louissaint at Stade Sylvio Cator (April 8, 2000) and the ceremony to scatter Dominique's ashes in the Artibonite River at Passe Caneau (April 15, 2000). Includes programs and schedules from both events.
    - Investigation, miscellaneous, 2000-2003, undated; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Miscellaneous material relating to the investigation into Jean Dominique's assassination. Includes a letter from Dr. Alix Charles on the death of Wilner Lalanne; the Mouvement National pour la Démocratie's statement on Dany Toussaint's accusations against Markington Philippe; a list of army officers who graduated together including Jean Lamy and Jean-Rénel Sanon (Dany Toussaint's lawyer); propaganda created by Dany Toussaint's supporters (Komite Solidarite ak Dany Toussaint). Includes the Bureau de Communication et Presse de la Présidence's April 2, 2002 announcement that Jean-Bertrand Aristide had renewed Judge Claudy Gassant. Also includes a transcript of Jean Dominique's editorial "Dany Toussaint, prend-il les enfants du bon dieu pour des canards sauvages?" Also includes Michèle Montas's 25 July, 2003 open letter to Josué Pierre-Louis concerning the lack of justice for Jean Dominique and Jean-Claude Louissaint, and for her boydguard Maxime Seïde, killed on 25 December 2002.
    - Justice for Jean Dominique, 2000-2002; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Open letters, petitions, and press statements commemorating the life of and calling for justice for Jean Dominique. Includes materials from the Association des Journalistes Haïtiens (AJH), National Coalition for Haitian Rights (NCHR), Fondation 30 Septembre, the Centre International des Droits de la Personne et du Développement Démocratique, Développement et Paix, Justice et Paix, the Class of 1969 of Columbia School of Journalism, POHDH, the Office de la Protection du Citoyen (OPC), and the Association Parents des Enfants Victimes d'Intoxication au Diéthylène Glycol, various coalitions of civil society organizations, and others, including unattributed sources. Also includes an English translation of Michèle Pierre-Louis's "Why Kill Jean Dominique?" which appeared in Chemins Critiques (Vol V, No. I).
    - Justice for Jean Dominique, miscellaneous and press, 2000-2013; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Additional materials about the ongoing search for justice for Jean Dominique. Includes Double Take magazine, El Nuevo Día, Newsday, the New York Times, and the Miami Herald. Also includes text of Michèle Montas's editorial "À quand la prochaine victime?" (3 November 2000) and her typewritten statement about the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights assistance with her and Jean Dominique's asylum case after the 28 November 1980 crackdown on the press in Haiti. Also includes pamphlet from the 10 December 2000 commemoration of the life and work of Jean Dominique held by NCHR in New York.
    - Pandiassou, 2001-2002; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Materials related to the Université Populaire Jean Dominique de Pandiassou (UPJDP).
    - Prix Jean Dominique, 2001-2002; 1 folder (Box 135)
      Materials relating to the UNESCO Prix Jean Dominique pour la Liberté de la Presse. Includes Radio Haiti journalist Jean Roland Chéry's submissions for the prize. Also includes a flier from a writing contest for young people, dedicated to the memory of Jean Dominique, organized by MICAH and sponsored by UNESCO, Radio Ibo, Radio Haiti, and SAKS.
    - Radio Haiti materials (1-11 of 22), 2000-2003; 11 folders (Box 136)
      Radio Haiti's written materials, including scripts, chronologies, and petitions, relating to the April 3, 2000 assassination of Jean Dominique and Jean-Claude Louissaint and the subsequent investigation and search for justice. Includes related material on the climate of impunity, violence against journalists, and impunity. In most cases, folders are organized chronologically by month.
    - Radio Haiti materials (12-22 of 22), 2000-2003; 11 folders (Box 137)
    - Reporters Sans Frontières, 2001-2003; 2 folders (Box 135)
      Press releases, publications, and communications from Reporters Sans Frontières on the assassination of Jean Dominique and the search for justice.
    - SAKS day planner: "Nou pap dòmi bliye", 2002; 1 folder (Box 138)
      2002 day planner ("ajennda popilè") by the Sosyete Animasyon Kominikasyon Sosyal (SAKS), entitled "Nou pap dòmi bliye." Commemorates several notable instances of injustice and impunity, including the assassination of Jean Dominique. Includes inscription to Dominique's elder sister, the writer Madeleine Paillère, from Joseph Georges of SAKS, who thanks her for her book "Inselbadjo."
    - Commemorative baseball caps, 2000-2001 (Box 157)
      Five baseball caps, three of which are printed "3 AVRIL 2000 JEAN DOMINIQUE TONBE BATAY-LA AP KONTINYE" and two of which are printed "USINE SUCRIÈRE J.L. DOMINIQUE DE DARBONNE."
    - Posters: Jean Dominique tonbe, batay la ap rapouswiv!, 2000; One tube (Tube 1)
      Two identical Tyvek posters, each measuring 71 x 47.25 inches, with head shot of Jean Dominique and the text "Jean Dominiqute tonbe, batay la ap rapouswiv!" ("Jean Dominique has fallen, the struggle goes on!")
    - Usine Sucrière Jean Léopold Dominique T-shirts, 2001 (Box 194)
      Four t-shirts commemorating the Usine Sucrière Jean Léopold Dominique (Jean Dominique Sugar Factory) in Darbonne, Léogâne, Haiti. The front says "USINE SUCRIERE J.L. DOMINIQUE DE DARBONNE" and the back says "Jean Dominique: Travayè, Ouvriye, Peyizan pap janm bliye-w" (Jean Dominique: Workers, Laborers, Peasants will never forget you).
  - Massacres, 1987-2003
    - Carrefour-Feuilles massacre (1999), 1999-2001; 4 folders (Box 138)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the May 28, 1999 Carrefour-Feuilles massacre in which police killed 11 people, and the subsequent trial.
    - Cazale massacre (1969), 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 138)
      See also: Duvalierism and Macoutism; Devoir de mémoire; National calendar
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on commemorations of the 1969 Cazale massacre and demands for justice for the victims. Includes materials from Association 27 Mars, Fondation Jean-Marie Vincent, and LAPPH, as well as an open letter from René Préval.
    - Danty massacre (1988), 1988-1991; 1 folder (Box 138)
      Radio Haiti materials on the 1988 massacre of peasants in Danty and demands for justice.
    - Gervais massacre, 1991; 1 folder (Box 138)
      See also: Peasant rights; Land conflict
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the 1991 Gervais massacre and search for justice. Includes declarations from several human rights and civil society groups.
    - Jean-Rabel massacre, 1987-2002; 12 folders (Box 139)
      See also: Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen; Land conflicts
      Radio Haiti materials, primarily on-air scripts, and external materials relating to the July 23, 1987 Jean-Rabel massacre. Includes materials from the lead-up to the massacre, include activities and demands for justice by Gwoupman Tèt Ansanm and the missionary team, the arrests of Michel Selmon and Renard Fénélon, and anti-communist propaganda. Includes statements, press releases, and petitions by the missionary team and grassroots peasants groups. Also includes a July 14, 1987 letter from the missionary team in Jean Rabel to Jean Dominique and Radio Haiti-Inter, denouncing their decision to allow Jean-Michel Richardson on the air. Includes Jean Dominique's handwritten notes on special programs on the massacre in the immediate aftermath, press releases, statements, and petitions by groups including Association nationale des agro-professionnels haïtiens (ANDAH), Tèt Ansanm, other grassroots peasant groups, Ministry of Information. Also includes reporting on anniversaries and commemorations of the massacre (including copies of "Chante Peyizan" and other publications by Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen). Includes report by the Commission d'Enquête Spéciale sur les Evenements de Jean-Rabel (August 1987), the ongoing search for justice for the victims. Includes material related to the nomination of Luckner Pierre as the investigating judge in the Jean-Rabel case, the objections of Monique Brisson due to Pierre's role in the 1982 execution of Richard Brisson, and the arrest of Pierre in 2000.
    - Pérodin massacre, 1990; 1 folder (Box 138)
      See also: Peasant movements; Land conflict
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the 1990 Pérodin massacre.
    - Piatre massacre, 1989-2003; 2 folders (Box 138)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the 1990 Piatre massacre, including land conflict between Olivier Nadal and peasant farmers, statements by Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen and CHADEL.
    - Raboteau massacre and trial, 1995-2002; 11 folders (Box 140)
      Radio Haiti materials (primarily scripts) and external documents relating to the Raboteau massacre (1994) and trial (2000). External materials include news, reports from the Commission Nationale de Vérité et de Justice, the Commission Justice et Paix, attorneys, POHDH, Fondation 30 Septembre, attorneys, Haitian grassroots human rights organizations, and others.
  - St. Jean Bosco massacre, 1988-2001
    - Franck Romain, 1988-1995; 2 folders (Box 141)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including external press, press releases from civil society groups, etc.) concerning former Port-au-Prince mayor and former Macoute Franck Romain's involvement in the St. Jean Bosco massacre, his asylum in Dominican Republic, and efforts to extradite him.
    - Letters, declarations, petitions, 1988; 2 folders (Box 141)
      Open letters, petitions, and declarations by Haitian grassroots groups and political parties reacting to the St. Jean Bosco massacre. Includes AJH, MDN, LAPPH, MPP, MIDH, KONAKOM, religious organizations, and others.
    - Press and press releases, 1988; 1 folder (Box 141)
      Press wires and press releases (US embassy, OEA, Fad'H) regarding the St. Jean Bosco massacre.
    - Radio Haiti texts, 1988; 4 folders (Box 141)
      Radio Haiti materials on the September 11, 1988 massacre at St. Jean Bosco at a mass led by Jean-Bertrand Aristide, and the aftermath of the massacre.
    - Radio Haiti texts, 1999-2001; 1 folder (Box 141)
      See also: Antoine Izméry assassination; September 11 under National Calendar.
      Radio Haiti scripts and research materials on commemorations of the 1988 St. Jean Bosco massacre, and the investigation and search for justice for the victims.
- Infrastructure, 1968-2003
  - Catastrophes, 1980-2003
    - Accidents, 1997-2002; 1 folder (Box 142)
      Radio Haiti materials related to accidents, mainly road accidents but also drownings, electrocutions, and other accidents.
    - Fierté Gonavienne, 1997-1998; 1 folder (Box 142)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the Fierté Gonavienne ferry disaster. External materials include press, statements by Haitian government, foreign embassies, Haitian organizations, and other entities.
    - Fires, 1989-2003; 1 folder (Box 142)
      Radio Haiti materials related to fires, both accidental and arson.
    - Hurricanes and storms, 1980; 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 142)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on hurricanes, storms, rains, flooding including Hurricane Allen (1980) and Hurricane Gilbert (1988) and the aftermath.
    - Hurricanes and storms, 1995-2003; 3 folders (Box 142)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on hurricanes, storms, rains, flooding, erosion. Includes much on Hurricane Georges and post-Georges aid for victims.
    - Maritime disasters, 1993-2002; 1 folder (Box 143)
      See also: Migrants at sea; Repatriation
      Radio Haiti materials on the Christ Vivant and l'Aviron disasters; Haitian boat accidents in Bahamas, Turks and Caicos. External press on the Neptune ferry accident, Christ Vivant, l'Aviron, and other maritime disasters.
    - Other catastrophes, 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and small amounts of external press related to other disasters, mainly landslides and building collapses, as well as lightning strikes, accidental poisonings, and disasters in general. Also includes disaster preparedness, including the Croix Rouge Haïtienne and OPDES (Organisation Pré-Désastre et de Secours).
    - Solar eclipse, 1998; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the 1998 solar eclipse, preparations for and concerns about the eclipse, and unforeseen consequences of the eclipse.
  - Public works, 1973-2003
    - Electricity, 1974-1984; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to electricity and the energy crisis, including the Péligre hydroelectric dam, Duvalier-era energy policy including energy costs. External materials include press, government announcements, communication between EDH (G. Khawly) and Alsthom Atlantique, among other items.
    - Electricity, 1986-1990; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to electricity, including Electricité d'Haïti (EDH) and conflicts with workers' union, strikes, energy problems and blackouts. Includes press releases and letters from EDH workers and grassroots groups, press releases from EDH.
    - Electricity, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to electricity, including Electricité d'Haïti (EDH), energy crisis, blackouts, rationing, the dam at Saint Mathurine, electricity distribution in rural Haiti.
    - Electricity, 2000-2003; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to electricity, including Electricité d'Haïti (EDH) and conflicts with workers' union, energy crisis and blackouts, the Péligre dam, electricity distribution in rural Haiti.
    - Irrigation and water capture, 1995-2003; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and one government publication on irrigation and water capture at Rivière Lastic (Fonds Parisien), Trois Rivières and La Plaine de l'Arcahaie.
    - MTPTC, 1973-1978; 1 folder + one oversized folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Ministère des Travaux Publics, Transports et Communications (MTPTC), including external press, an MTPTC report on urban traffic, roads and road construction, transport.
    - MTPTC, 1987-1990; 1995-2002; 7 folders (Box 144)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including MTPTC press releases and external press) relating to the Ministère des Travaux Publics, Transports et Communications (MTPTC), various infrastructure and public works projects (including roads, unauthorized urban construction), as well as the role of external aid and private contracts. Folders arranged by year.
    - Projects, general, 1998-2003; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti materials and small amounts of external press related to infrastructure and development projects in general, including in poor neighborhoods of Port-au-Prince and various rural areas.
    - Public housing, 1987-2001; 1 folder (Box 143)
      Radio Haiti and external materials about public housing projects under the Entreprise Publique de Promotion de Logements Sociaux, including projects in Cité Soleil for residents whose homes were burned down by FRAPH on 27 December 1993.
    - Public plazas, parks, 1999-2002; 1 folder (Box 145)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about construction, maintenance, and degradation of public parks and plazas.
    - Unité Centrale de Gestion (UCG), 1995-2000; 2 folders (Box 145)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Unité Centrale de Gestion's projects under Paul Latortue, including roads and potable water projects (especially the Inter-American Development Bank-funded PURE II project).
    - Water, 1986-1989; 1995-2003; 3 folders (Box 145)
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials (including CAMEP and government documents) relating to potable water and water distribution, water contamination, lack of potable water, CAMEP (Centrale Métropolitaine d'Eau Potable) and SNEP (Service National de l'Eau Potable).
  - Telecommunications, 1968-2003
    - Affaire ACN, 1997-1999; 1 folder (Box 145)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials, including press releases, relating to conflict with Teleco and Conatel, Internet, fraud, and disconnection.
    - BRH/Teleco, 1996; 1 folder (Box 145)
      External materials including memorandum of the BRH (Banque de la Republique d'Haïti), communications of the BRH with Teleco, inventory, and budgeting.
    - General, 1968; 1988-1991; 1 folder (Box 145)
      External materials relating to Teleco (Télécommunications d'Haïti), CONATEL (Conseil Nationale des Télécommunications), including government declarations (François Duvalier, E. Pascal Trouillot), press releases, and press.
    - General, 1995; 1 folder (Box 145)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to telecommunications, including Teleco coverage in Jérémie, Cayes, La Gonâve, and elsewhere; Teleco workers' union, among other subjects. Includes press releases from government, Teleco.
    - General, 1996; 2 folders (Box 146)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to telecommunications, including bylaws of CONATEL, conference documents from CONATEL, press releases from CONATEL, expansion of Teleco coverage, Teleco finances, pricing, reforms, corruption in Teleco, Teleco workers' strikes, Radio Haiti scripts about Teleco, external press.
    - General, 1997; 1 folder (Box 146)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on Teleco crisis, including disrepair, workers' strike, and administrative changes. Includes external press.
    - General, 1998; 1 folder (Box 146)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials, including press releases and external press, relating to Teleco, privatization of Teleco, Teleco workers' union, strikes, fraud, financing, international coverage, coverage in rural Haiti, vandalism, Internet, technology fairs, CONATEL, cellular expansion including RECTEL, SOETEL.
    - General, 1999; 1 folder (Box 146)
      See also: Affaire ACN
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials. Including press releases, external press coverage, rise of other telecommunication companies including DIGICOM and Haïtel, vandalism, and cellular network expansion.
    - General, 2000-2003; 1 folder (Box 146)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials, including press releases from CONATEL and external press, relating to Internet, Teleco, finances, rural expansion, privatization and mergers, and administrative changes.
    - Téléco investigation, 1990; 1 folder (Box 146)
      Three issues of Le Matin featuring articles about Jean Dominique's investigation into fraud at Téléco.
  - Transportation, 1977-2002
    - Air transport, 1989-2003; 1 folder (Box 146)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about air transport, airlines and airports. Includes Office National de l'Aviation Civile (OFNAC), Autorité Aeroportuaire Nationale.
    - Maritime transport, 1991-2002; 1 folder (Box 147)
      See also: Maritime disasters
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about maritime transport, specifically SEMANAH (Service Maritime et Navigation d'Haïti.)
    - Ports, 1977-1979; 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 147)
      See also: Customs; TEVASA affair
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about ports and the Autorité Nationale Portuaire (APN), Administration Portuaire Publique (APP), and private ports, including St. Louis du Sud. Includes issues relating to APN administration and workers' unions, customs, counterfeit, and other topics.
    - Roads and bridges, 1991; 1995-2002; 1 folder (Box 147)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (1991 government decree in Le Moniteur) on roads, road construction, road repairs, bridge collapses, Centre National des Equipements (CNE).
    - Service Plus, 1998-2001; 1 folder (Box 147)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the private bus company Service Plus and Duclos Bénissoit.
    - Traffic and transport, 1995-2002; 1 folder (Box 147)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about traffic and transportation, including strikes by drivers' unions.
- International Relations, 1956-2003
  - Bilateral, 1972-2003
    - Belgium, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 148)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-Belgium relations and bilateral cooperation.
    - Canada, 1986-2003; 3 folders (Box 148)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-Canada relations and bilateral cooperation. Includes development aid, military intervention, particular relationships between Haiti and Quebec/Montreal, accusations of anti-Haitian sentiment on the part of Denis Paradis, among other subjects.
    - Caribbean, 1972-2002; 2 folders (Box 148)
      See also: Immigration; Francophonie; CARICOM
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti's relationship and bilateral cooperation with countries and territories in the Caribbean (South-South cooperation). Includes Guadeloupe, Saint-Martin, Jamaica, St. Kitts, Bahamas, Barbados, Puerto Rico, Turks and Caicos, Suriname, Trinidad and Tobago.
    - Cuba, 1977-1991; 1 folder (Box 148)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-Cuba relations and bilateral cooperation.
    - Cuba, 1996-2003; 5 folders (Box 148)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-Cuba relations and bilateral cooperation. Includes foreign aid, technical assistance, Cuban doctors, Jean-Bertrand Aristide's and René Préval's visits to Cuba, Haitian scholarship recipients, and repatriations.
    - Cuba: Castro speeches, 2003; 1 folder (Box 149)
      French translations of several speeches by Fidel Castro in 2003, circulated by the Cuban embassy in Haiti.
    - France, 1977-2002; 4 folders (Box 149)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-France relations and bilateral cooperation. Includes economic aid, military intervention, cultural cooperation (e.g. Institut Français), among other subjects.
    - Japan, 1996-2003; 2 folders (Box 149)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Haiti-Japan relations and bilateral cooperation. Includes economic aid and agricultural assistance, among other subjects.
    - Latin America, 1987-2001; 2 folders (Box 149)